You've seen how a
basic RNN works.
In this video, you learn about
the gated recurrent unit,
which has a modification
to the RNN hidden layer
that makes it much better at
capturing long-range
connections and helps
a lot with the vanishing
gradient problems.
Let's take a look. You've
already seen the formula
for computing the activations
at time t of an RNN.
It's the activation function
applied to the parameter W_a
times the activations for
a previous time
sediment the current
input and then plus the bias.
I'm going to draw
this as a picture.
The RNN units I'm going
to draw as a picture,
drawn as a box which
inputs a of t minus 1,
deactivation for the last
timestep and also inputs x^t,
and these two go together,
and after some weights
and after this type of
linear calculation,
if g is a tanh
activation function,
then after the tanh,
it computes the output
of activation, a.
The output activation a^t
might also be parsed to
say a softmax unit or
something that could then
be used to outputs y hat ^t.
This is maybe a visualization
of the RNN unit of
the hidden layer of the
RNN in terms of a picture.
I want to show you this picture
because we're going to
use a similar picture to
explain the GRU or the
gated recurrent unit.
A lot of ideas of GRUs were due
to these two papers respectively
by Junyoung Chung,
Caglar, Gulcehre,
KyungHyun Cho, and
Yoshua Bengio.
Sometime is going to
refer to this sentence,
which we'd seen in
the last video,
to motivate that given
a sentence like this,
you might need to
remember the cat was
singular to make
sure you understand
why that was rather than
were as of the cat was
for the cats were full.
As we read in this sentence
from left to right,
the GRU unit is going to have
a new variable called C,
which stands for cell,
for memory cell.
What the memory cell do is
it will provide a bit of memory.
Remember, for example,
whether cat was
singular or plural,
so that when it gets much
further into the sentence,
it can still work on
the consideration
whether the subject
of the sentence was
singular or plural.
At time t, the memory cell
will have some value c of
t. What we'll see is
that the GRU unit will
actually output an activation
value a of t that's
equal to c of t.
For now I wanted to
use different symbols c and
a to denote the
memory cell value and
the output activation value
even though they're
the same and I'm using
this notation because
when we talked about
LSTMs a little bit later,
these will be two
different values.
But for now, for the GRU c of t
is equal to the output
activation a of
t. These are the equations that
govern the computations
of a GRU unit.
At every time step,
we're going to consider
an overwriting
the memory cell with a
value c tilde of t. This
going to be a candidate
for replacing c of
t. We're going to compute
this using an
activation function,
tanh of w_c,
and so that's the
parameter matrix w_c
and we'll pass it as
parameter matrix.
The previous value of
the memory cell, the
activation value,
as well as the current input
value x^t and then plus a bias.
C tilde of t is going to be
a candidate for replacing c^t.
Then the key, really the
important idea of the GRU,
it will be that
we'll have a gate.
The gate I'm going
to call Gamma_u.
This is the capital
Greek alphabet, Gamma_u,
and u stands for update gate.
This would be a value
between 0 and 1.
To develop your intuition
about how GRUs work,
think of Gamma_u this gate
value as being always 0 or 1.
Although in practice,
your computer with
a sigmoid function
applied to this.
Remember that the sigmoid
function looks like this,
as value is always
between 0 and 1.
For most of the possible
ranges of the input,
the sigmoid function
is either very,
very close to 0 or very,
very close to 1.
For intuition, think of Gamma as
being either 0 or 1
most of the time.
I chose the alphabet
Gamma for this
because if you look
at a gated fence,
it looks a bit like
this, I guess.
Then there are a lot of
Gammas in this fence.
That's why your
Gamma_u we're going to
use to denote the gate.
Also Greek alphabet G,
like G for gate, so G for
Gamma and G for gate.
Then next the key part of
the GRU is this equation,
which is that we have come up
with a candidate where
we're thinking of
updating C using c tilde
and then the gate will decide
whether or not we
actually update it.
The way to think about it
is maybe this memory cell C
is going to be set to
either zero or one
depending on whether the
word you're conserving,
really the subject of the
sentence is singular or plural.
Because it's singular,
let's say that we
set this to one and
if it was plural,
maybe we'll set this as a zero
and then the GRU unit will
memorize the value of the
C^t all the way until here,
where this is still
equal to one and
so that tells it was singular
so use the choice was.
The job of the gate, of gamma u,
is to decide when do
you update this value.
In particular, when you
see the phrase the cat,
you know that you're talking
about a new concept,
the subject of the sentence cat.
That would be a good time
to update this bit and then
maybe when you're done
using it the cat was full,
then you know I don't
need to memorize
anymore I can just forget that.
The specific equation we'll use
for the GRU is the following;
which is that the actual
value of C^t would be
equal to this gate times
the candidate value
plus one minus
the gate times the old
value C^t minus one.
Notice that if the gate,
if this update value
of z equal to one,
then is saying set
the new value of C^t
equal to this candidate value
so that's like over here,
set the gate equal to one
so go ahead and update that bit.
Then for all of these
values in the middle,
you should have the gate equal
zero so do the same,
don't update it,
just hang on to the
old value because
if gamma u is equal to zero,
then this would be zero and
this will be one and
so it's just setting
C^t equal to the old value
even as you scan the
sentence from left to right.
When the gate is equal to
zero as saying, don't update it,
just hang on to the value
and don't forget what it's
value was and so that way,
even when you get all
the way down here,
hopefully you've
just been setting
C^t equal C^t minus one
all along and still memorizes
the cat was singular.
Let me also draw a picture
to denote the GRU unit.
By the way, when you look in
online blog posts and
textbooks and tutorials,
these types of pictures are
quite popular for explaining
GRUs as well as we'll
see later LSTM units.
I personally find the equations
easier to understand in
the pictures so if the picture
doesn't make sense
don't worry about it,
but I'll just draw it in
case it helps some of you.
The GRU unit inputs
C^t minus one for the
previous time step
and this happens to be equal to
80 minus one so it
takes us as input.
Then it also takes
this input X^t.
Then these two
things get combined
together and with
some appropriate waiting
and some tonnage.
This gives you c tilde t,
which is a candidate for
replacing C^t and then we have
a different set
of parameters and
through a sigmoid
activation function,
this gives you gamma u,
which is the update
gate and then finally,
all of these things combined
together through
another operation.
I won't write out
the formula but
this box here which
are shaded in purple,
represents this equation
which we had down there.
That's what this purple
operation represents
and it takes as input
the gate value,
the candidate new value,
that's the gate value again,
and the old value for C^t
it takes as input this,
this and this, and together they
generate the new value
for the memory cell.
That's C^t equals a.
If you wish, you could also
use this impulses through
a soft-max or something to make
some prediction for Y^t
so that is the GRU units.
These are slightly
simplified version of it.
What is remarkably good
at is through the gate
deciding that when you're
scanning the sentence
from left to right,
say that that's a
good time to update
one to the memory
cell and enter,
not change it,
until you get to the point
where you really needed to use
this memory cell that you
had set even much
earlier in the sentence.
Now, because the gate is quite
easy to set to zero so long as
this quantity is a
large negative value,
then up to numerical round-off,
the update gate will
be essentially zero,
very close to zero.
When that's the case,
then this update
equation and sub
setting C^t equals
C^t minus one and so
this is very good at maintaining
the value for the cell
and because gamma can
be so close to zero,
can be 0.000001 or even
smaller than that.
it doesn't suffer from much of
a vanishing gradient
problem because
in say gamma so close to zero
that this becomes essentially
C^t equals C^t minus
one and the value of C^t
is maintained pretty much
exactly even across
many times that.
This can help significantly
with the vanishing
gradient problem
and therefore allowing
your network to
learn even very
long-range dependencies,
such as the cat and
was are related
even if they are separated by
a lot of words in the middle.
Now, I just want to talk over
some more details of
how you implement this.
In the equations have written,
C^t can be a vector.
If you have 100-dimensional
hidden activation value,
then C^t can be
100-dimensional Zai,
and so C^t would also be
the same dimension and
Gamma would also be
the same dimension as
the other things I'm
drawing in boxes.
In that case, these asterisks
are actually element-wise
multiplication.
Here, if the gates
is 100-dimensional
vector, what it is,
is really 100-dimensional
vector of bits,
the value is mostly 0 and 1,
that tells you of this
100-dimensional memory cell,
which are the bits
you want to update.
Of course in practice,
Gamma won't be exactly`0 and 1,
sometimes I'll say values
in the middle as well.
There is convenient
for intuition to
think of it as mostly taking
on values that are
pretty much exactly 0,
or pretty much exactly 1.
What these element-wise
multiplications do is it
just tells you GRU
which are the dimensions of
your memory cell vector to
update at every time step.
You can choose to keep some bits
constant while
updating other bits.
For example, maybe
you'll use one-bit to
remember the singular
or plural cat,
and maybe you'll
use some other bits
to realize that you're
talking about food.
Because we talked about
eating and talk about foods,
then you'd expect to
talk about whether the
cat is full later.
You can use different
bits and change
only a subset of the bits
at every point in time.
You now understand the most
important ideas that a GRU.
What I presented on
this slide is actually
a slightly simplified GRU unit.
Let me describe
the full GRU unit.
To do that, let me copy
the three main equations.
This one, this one,
and this one to the next slide.
Here they are. For
the full GRU units,
I'm sure they'll make
one change to this,
which is for the first
equation which was calculating
the candidate new value
for the memory cell,
I'm going to add just one term.
They pushed that a
little bit to the right,
and I'm going to
add one more gate.
This is another gate
Gamma r. You can think of r
as standing for relevance.
This gate Gamma r tells
you how relevant is C^t
minus 1 to computing the
next candidate for C^t.
This gate Gamma r
is computed pretty
much as you expect with a
new parameter matrix w _r,
and then the same things
as input x_t plus b_r.
As you can imagine, there are
multiple ways to design these
types of neural networks,
and why do we have Gamma r?
Why not use a simpler version
from the previous slides?
It turns out that
over many years,
researchers have
experimented with
many different possible
versions of how
to design these units
to try to have longer
range connections.
To try to have
model long-range effects and
also address vanishing
gradient problems.
The GRU is one of
the most commonly used
versions that researchers
have converged to
and then found as
robust and useful for
many different problems.
If you wish, you
could try to invent
a new versions of these
units if you want,
but the GRU is a standard one,
is just commonly used.
Although you can imagine that
researchers have
tried other versions
that are similar
but not exactly the
same as what I'm writing
down here as well.
The other common version
is called an LSTM,
which stands for Long,
Short-term Memory,
which we'll talk about
in the next video.
But GRUs and LSTMs are
two specific instantiations of
this set of ideas that
are most commonly used.
Just one note on notation.
I tried to define
a consistent notation to
make these ideas
easier to understand.
If you look at the
academic literature,
sometimes you'll see people
use an alternative notation,
there would be H tilde there, U,
R and H to refer to these
quantities as well.
They try to use a more
consistent notation between GRUs
and LSTMs as well as using
a more consistent notation,
Gamma to refer to the gains
to hopefully make these
ideas easier to understand.
That's it for the GRU,
for the Gated Recurrent Unit.
This is one of the ideas in RNNs
that has enabled
them to become much
better at capturing very
long-range dependencies
as made RNNs much
more effective.
Next, as I briefly mentioned,
the other most commonly used
deviation of this
class of ideas is
something called the LSTM
unit or the Long,
Short-term Memory unit.
Let's take a look at
that in the next video.